[Music]
[Applause]
what's up fitness friends so garyvee has
been doing this cool thing on his
channel called
overrated underrated and i thought it
would be awesome to do that
on my channel and today's will be just
pertaining to glute training but
i may do this you know semi-frequently
as it pertains to other topics as well
in fitness but
again today's is only glute training i
have alex here my camera guy
ready to roll off the questions so let's
do it
underrated carbs carbs underrated squats
squats i would say properly rated people
love squats they're a pretty good group
builder
restriction training bfr massively
overrated
total body training total body training
uh underrated
naps naps very underrated flexible
dieting
flexible dieting also underrated lunges
lunges properly rated
they're people love them they're great
[Music]
bands and glute loops are a tough one
because they're underrated by bros
but they're overrated by fit chicks so
the net balance would be properly rated
deadlifts i think
are overrated and and here's why so many
people hurt themselves with deadlifts
you'll see the best results
if you are injury pain and injury freak
because pain inhibits muscle activation
so
deadlifts are great just don't get
carried away and use poor form free
weights
free weights underrated donuts donuts
are overrated
my our industry has an obsession with
donuts i kind of think it's funny
because i love donuts just as much as
everyone but the goal is to
build muscular glutes not just fat
everywhere so
overrated machines machines i'm going to
go with underrated uh i think
especially the bros think machines are
stupid a lot of them and
the machines are great like the smith
machine is amazing
plate loaded machines are amazing
electric muscle stimulation devices ems
ems devices very overrated protein
protein underrated you need one gram per
pound of body weight per day
so if you weigh 120 120 pounds
and you eat three times a day you need
40 grams per serving that's tough for a
lot of women to get
mind muscle connection mind muscle
connection i would say
is overrated you know it's it's
important but
mind muscle connection without
progressive overload isn't going to
yield that good results
sleep sleep i would say sleep is
properly rated but some people in in our
industry are like you need nine to ten
hours of sleep a day no you don't but if
you're the type that sleeps
six or seven hours and feels great
that's okay also
don't be afraid to nap rest days rest
days okay
it's a tough one i would say underrated
with
especially with the uh you know like
exercise addicts who have to train
glutes every single day
you know you got to take a day off at
least one day a week but two to three
days off preferably to gain strains and
set pr's woody building machines bloody
motor machine
i personally don't like it that much but
my clients love it
so i think if you're a gym owner and you
get one nobody's gonna be mad at you
so properly rated crossfit crossfit uh i
would say overrated for glutes
uh you love crossfit crossfit's badass
but
for glutes they could do better they
could do better if they wanted to they
just add in hip thrusts
but they don't care back extensions back
extensions underrated one of the best
glute exercises they're out there
especially if you learn how to do it
right
but uh people you know but the
bodybuilding bros do them for back still
and don't try to use their glutes
uh branched chain amino acids very
overrated
uh it's more about getting your total
amount of protein
if you get your protein bcaas don't do
much peanut butter
peanut butter uh i would say overrated
again i love peanut butter i eat so much
peanut butter but our
industry is obsessed with like donuts
and peanut butter and
yeah again the goal is to be lean some
peanut butter is fine just don't go
crazy
kickbacks are a similar answer here
underrated with the bros they all think
it's stupid
but properly rated with women women love
it i actually think it works better for
women too
because when i do kickbacks i'm so
strong at it
that but this the opposite hip flexor
can't stabilize properly like i could
use the whole stack but
this hip flexor takes the load so i
think there's a you know
i think there's a good explanation why
the bros don't like it as much as
women see the hip abduction machine
seated hip production machine
same answer the bros think it's stupid
women love it and it's great
so underrated with the bros but all
women love it because they feel it
working their glutes low low glute
activation
low load glute activation overrated we
don't do any
at my gym because every every exercise
is going to have high glute activation
you know and we utilize progressive
overload with it definitely warm up
but with the warm-up we're trying to you
know go for mobility more than
activation you're just trying to
kind of like do dynamic stretches and
then you do the workout creatine
i would say overrated there's so much
research in support of it everyone knows
it works but it doesn't work
that well it doesn't do that much it's a
million studies showing it's effective
but it's not it's not like
mandatory most of my clients don't take
it progressive overload
progressive overload underrated my girls
who have seen the best results have
gained a ton of strength that's what
caused their glutes to transform you
know tension on the muscle is king
band burnout's overrated everyone loves
them my clients love them
you're a personal trainer you finish off
the workout with with a band burnout
they're gonna love you but i don't think
it does my
i haven't seen any evidence but they
love it so i do it but i don't think it
does that much body parts
butter bar splits overrated most
bodybuilders do it
i'm not gonna say they're doing it wrong
but for glutes you need to train glutes
frequently
so if you just have one leg day a week
then yeah you're leaving a lot on the
table for glutes i like total body
training for glute or at least a lower
upper split
i like and even with the lower upper i
like lower upper lower upper glute
kettlebell kiddo swings uh i love
kettlebell swings
but overrated for glute development just
do hip thrusts
good mornings overrated for glute
development it's more of a hamstring
exercise but some people love them so
that pushes sub push is overrated it's
there's no eccentric phase uh
i think it's hard for progressive
overload because it's like you know
every
every ground has a different friction so
yeah overrated
capable through is overrated just to hit
the rest cereal
cereal underrated carbs are good for
booty just
don't go crazy muscle confusion muscle
confusion so
overrated you know that gives people an
excuse to
have no strategy and just go into the
gym and change stuff up every day that's
recipe for
failure if you're trying to build your
glutes whey protein whey protein
underrated way it's the best quality
protein
if you can stomach it take it frequently
it's great the pump
the pump i love getting a pump love
getting a pump but i still think it's
overrated you know brad schoenfeld and i
wrote a paper on
explaining the potential mechanisms but
we don't have a lot of
evidence in support of it because it's
really hard to measure whether it's
actually building muscle or not we have
theoretical rationale but i think too
many people concern themselves more with
the pump than progressive overload
intermittent fasting intermittent
fasting overrated you need protein
at least a few times a day ideally and
you don't want to train you know while
you're hungry so it works great for fat
loss
and some people can get jacked on it but
i don't think it's optimal for building
muscle especially for building glutes
body weight
body weight floor exercises uh i would
say
they're overrated they they're not hard
enough you need
progressive overload but i will say you
can still get nice glutes with body
weight training like
sideline hip raises pistol squats single
leg hip thrusts they're all great
but most people do wimpy workouts with
that
and not don't push it hard enough
periodization
okay if you type in periodization onto
google and like look
you know with strength training you get
all these crazy charts and
systems and methods and you know you get
all these um you know
like block classical or linear and like
you know
dup and all this i think that's
overrated uh
in fact a lot of my clients i try to
write my clients programs
and they when i write them programs a
lot of them see less results than when i
just
wing it but the problem the the thing
with that is i've been coaching for so
many years and i've been lifting for so
many years when i
say i wing it there's a lot of strategy
behind that
my wing is like a beginner wing a
beginner wing is like uh i'm gonna do
some of this exercise then i'll do some
of this
then i'll do some of this then the next
day it's like i'll do this first then
i'll do this and there's no rhyme or
reason to anything
with my winging it it's like i'm always
trying to get them strong or at
hip thrust squats deadlifts lunges back
extensions
abduction and uh and i know how to do it
just you know by
seeing how they feel and everything so
if you know what you're doing you have a
system whether you know it or not you
know you're always prioritizing certain
things or trying to improve
certain qualities so you're periodizing
whether you know it or not
setting prs pr stands for personal
records setting prs
underrated plyometrics overrated super
slow training
super slow training they're almost
everything works well
in strength training there's like
support in the literature but
super slow training i think is this
dumbest thing i
i just i would never do it with any
client definitely overrated
forced reps has a great theoretical
rationale
but the problem is even training to
failure doesn't have a lot of support in
the literature
so why if if training a failure doesn't
is it necessary why would forced reps be
necessary
overrated feeling the burn overrated i
love feeling the burn
but i think uh people get more focused
on that than gaining strength and using
good form
b stance exercises underrated yeah they
work great
they're kind of like a bridge between
true single leg stuff
and bilateral stuff not many people know
about them drop sets
drop sets underrated uh well i was just
say underrated when you're in
a time crunch that's the most efficient
way to get in a good workout you know
quickly so
when you when you're in a time crunch do
drop sets they're great cbd oil
cbd i'm gonna go overrated uh you know
i've looked at the
my clients swear by it but i look at the
literature there's not a lot of evidence
for it but you know anecdotally people
swear by it for helping them sleep or
helping them feel better but i don't
know
the research isn't there yet bulking and
cutting bulking and cutting i'm going to
say overrated you know all the
bodybuilders love to bulk and cut but
i think for most women you could bulk
and cut but stay in a narrow range
like you know bodybuilders might bulk up
to here and cut down to here
you know don't don't bulk so how much
and don't cut so much
kind of stay with stay more around the
maintenance zone
and uh you know i don't it's like
the the rationale behind bulky and
cutting is you know
if you're so low in body fat you can't
gain muscle but
a lot of the women are how that i work
with they're never hovering it below 10
body fat so they don't need to bulk and
cut so much they stay in a good
uh hormonal zone for building muscle
their master
oh definitely overrated uh stairmaster
step mill i think cardio in general
doesn't build glutes
weight training does broncos frog pump i
would say properly
properly rated because the the people
who love frog pumps like me it's
my favorite it i feel my glutes more
with frog pumps anything but probably at
least a third of people don't feel frog
pumps much
it's all due to your hip anatomy so some
people can't stand them due to their hip
anatomy some people love them due to
their hip anatomy
so properly rated volume volume
overrated i think
a lot of people rely on volume to try to
feel like they got a good workout and
kind of as a substitute for pushing it
hard or effort you got to push it really
hard you can't just
do tons of sets to to make up for your
lack of
training intensity blue ham races glue
ham raises
overrated it's a hamstring exercise it's
knee flexion why would it work the
glutes that much
1rm max hip thrust
overrated i i do them in you know my my
my clients do them all the time because
i'm always preparing them for
strong lifting events but so i like the
way my clients do them because i make
sure they lock out
but the way you see them on the internet
people aren't using good form they're
arching their backs they're
not locking out their legs are quivering
they're doing three quarter reps and
calling it a one rep
max and they're not reaching full hip
extension so the way it's done
in by the masses is overrated circuits
circuits
overrated sprinting sprinting overrated
you know nothing works the glutes like
weight training
you know hip thrusts and squats and
lunges and back extensions and abduction
and you can control those they're a
controlled environment sprinting is
uh you know god the best sprinters in
the world are
like on the ground for 0.08 seconds
people will never sprint for 10 years
and then go out and run
go to the track and run like 100 meter
all-out sprints and then they hurt
themselves they pull a hammy
they pull a hip flexor they tear a
calves something like that
and uh it's just it's a and it's risky
it's it's you know that's the
most powerful one of the most powerful
actions you can do
as a human and so i just think it's too
risky and people point out while
sprinters have great glutes but yeah how
did sprinter's glutes look
before weights were popular it's the
weights making sprinters glutes look
nice not
not sprinting so overrated single leg
training
single leg training underrated uh
especially by the bros
bilateral is fun you use more weight but
single leg
makes sure you're you don't get too out
of balance from one side to the next it
keeps you honest
definitely underrated coffee or energy
drinks coughing energy drinks
properly rated some people drink too
many
too much caffeine but it helps you get a
better workout
ketogenic diets keto overrated
uh carbs help fuel good workouts and you
don't need
to be in ketosis to lose fat recalping
recomping
well okay i would say it's underrated
but for building glutes
glute just sheer glute size just bulk
like crazy but
you're trying to look your best you want
the nicest aesthetically looking glutes
so i think recomping is
underrated because you want to be lean
you want
a nice lean pleasing physique and so
you could stay at the same body weight
and just make sure you're eating getting
your protein in and getting stronger and
you'll recomp and you'll just look a
little bit better
every month none of this blue drive
machine the nautilus glute drive i would
say
is i love the nautilus glute drive it's
my favorite but
my clients don't like it because the
mainly because the pad hurts them
so i would say overrated uh i have seen
it a lot of
like some gyms will have like two or
three of them they get used a lot but
then i'll talk to the customers and
they'll be like the pad hurts me
i just wish they made a solution for
that kettlebells kettlebells
overrated i love kettlebell deadlifts i
love
swings i think kettlebells are great for
overall functional training and
athleticism
you know i don't want to talk it's just
like crossfit i love crossfit but
yeah crossfit's not ideal for glutes and
kettlebell training alone isn't ideal
for glutes i
i like all tools and i used to love
kettlebell deadlifts but now i have my
t-belt
the t-bell is better for progressive
overload because you can load it you
know like two and a half pounds at a
time if you wanted
kettlebell swings won't build glutes
like hip thrusts will and
kettlebell deadlifts won't build glutes
like like regular deadlifts will so
overrated temple work overrated you know
i hear people in my industry be like you
need to do
a two second lowering phase and a one
second lifting phase
and it's like so three seconds per rep
that's not
ever seen in real life you know in real
life well it depends on the exercise but
in real life people do
you know say you do a set of 20 hip
thrusts that set tends to last 20
seconds
or like 25 seconds it's not three
seconds pretty
a set of 20 hip dust does not last 60
seconds neither do frog pumps neither do
band work
maybe a set of squats do but that's a
long
range of motion exercise so it just
depends on the exercise but
i don't specify temp how to do tempo
just do it how you like unless we do
pause reps then i'd specify the tempo or
if we do eccentric accentuated wraps
which i might say a four second lowering
but
otherwise lift how it feels naturally
for you short rest periods
short rest periods massively overrated
you need rest to recuperate and set prs
you're not going to be able to give a
set your all if you
rest 60 seconds if you're really
training close to failure
leg press i love it works the legs well
you'll feel the glutes but i don't i
think it's overrated as a glute exercise
i think it's more of a leg exercise a
quad a quad movement
pre-exhaustion pre-exhaustion
interestingly
the weeder principle pre-exhaustion was
like do
do you know flies or or peck deck or
crossovers before you do bench
pre-exhaust your pecs and then you'll
get a better workout doing bench press
and the research showed the pecs are
fatigued you actually
end up using your triceps and front
delts more so you can work
backwards from that and say all right if
you're trying to pre-exhaust
in order to work more glutes you could
actually do a hamstring or like a
movement that fatigues a synergist so
we've had some people do things like leg
curls before they do hip thrusts
and they end up feeling their glutes
more so i think it's underrated in this
case and has the potential
to help a lot of people it's just not
there's not research in support of this
yet for glutes
knee banded barbell hip dust everyone
loves them i think it's
underrated for upper glute development
and overrated for lower glute
development
that's being real nitpicky uh but yeah
the bands will increase glute medius and
upper gluteus maximus emg
but then they might fatigue you faster
so then you don't do as many reps which
could be robbing your gl
lower gluteus maximus of some gains but
that's that's theoretical
german volume training german volume
training gvt that's 10 sets
of 10. i think it's overrated in most
scenarios in fact there's research that
shows that
five sets of ten built more muscle and
strength than ten sets of ten
ten sets of ten is too excessive in most
scenarios but i actually think
with hip thrust you can do it i think
that with the glutes can handle 10 by 10
hip thrusts as long as you're not
killing yourself you know if you start
out with some reasonable but but either
way i still think it's overrated because
yeah you should if you're going to do 10
sets you should spread it out with more
exercises and you'll end up
hitting more glute fibers so i hope you
enjoyed this edition of overrated
underrated by coach bc
uh shout out to gary vaynerchuk for
coming up with this
let me know if you like this and i'll do
more of it i know some of you wanted
more in-depth explanations but then this
would have been an hour long
if you liked the video give it a thumbs
up comment
subscribe to my channel we're working on
a lot of stuff behind the scenes
uh it's been a lot of work kind of
revamping my youtube channel but
i got a ton of great stuff to come so
stay tuned
now if this video intrigued you and you
would like to train
under my system using my principles then
i invite you to click on the link below
and subscribe to booty by brett and join
the thousands of other happy members
who are seeing amazing results